A Guide to the Carrington Family Papers, 1756-1843
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Carrington Family Papers, 1756-1843
Library of Virginia
20459
0.45 cubic feet, negative photostats
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Mrs. Flournoy X. Barksdale, Randolph, Virginia, 15 September 1932.
Biographical/Historical Information
Paul Carrington (5 March 1733-23 June 1818) was born in Cumberland County, Virginia, to George Carrinton (1711-1785) and Anne Mayo Carrington (d. 1785). He moved to that part of Lunenburg County, Virginia, which became Charlotte County, Virginia, and established his plantation Mulberry Hill. He represented Charlotte County in the House of Burgesses from 1765 to 1776, and in the five Virginia Revolutionary Conventions from 1774 to 1776. Carrington then represented Charlotte, Halifax, and Prince Edward Counties in the Virginia Senate from 1776 to 1778. He served as a judge on the General Court and the Supreme Court of Appeals. Carrington and his wife Margaret Read Carrington (1739-1776) had five children, including Clement Carrington (1762-1847). Clement Carrington served in Lee's Legion during the American Revolution and was wounded at the battle of Eutaw Springs. Clement Carrington served as a county judge, a colonel in the Virginia militia, and in the House of Delegates from 1789 to 1790. He and his wife Jane Watkins Poage had four children, including Anne (Nancy) Cabell Carrington (McPhail) (1811-1880). Paul Carrington and his second wife Priscilla Sims (1776-1803) had six children, including Henry Carrington (1793-1867), who served as a colonel in the Virginia militia, Lettice Carrington (Coles) (b. 1798), and Robert Carrington (1802-1845) married Joanna T. Bouldin (1800-1870).
Scope and Content
Papers, 1756-1843, of the Carrington family of Lunenburg and Charlotte Counties, Virginia, consisting of abstracts, accounts, bonds, deeds, field notes, judicial records, land grants, land surveys, letters, plats, powers of attorney, receipts, subscriptions, and tax records. Abstracts, bonds, deeds, field notes, land surveys, plats, and powers of attorney mostly involve lands purchased by Paul Carrington (1733-1818), Clement Carrington (1762-1847), and Robert Carrington (1802-1845) in Charlotte County. Deeds are also for lands purchased in Lunenburg and Halifax Counties, Virginia, and Person County, North Carolina. There is a land grant based on a military warrant in Kentucky, and a letter from James Taylor regarding that military warrant. Collection also contains deeds for the purchase of slaves. Accounts and receipts record payment of monies owed to and by the Carringtons, including postal fees. Judicial records and tax records include payment of monies to the county court for fees and taxes. Some 1828 receipts concern the purchase of a tombstone for Thomas Read. Papers also include a letter, 2 September 1786, from Paul Carrington to John Daniel concerning remarks made by Carrington about Edmund Read as a delegate in the General Assembly which Daniel mistakenly believed referred to him; a pedigree for a horse that Clement Carrington purchased; and subscriptions for the Richmond Enquirer and the Richmond Compiler.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Deed and Patent, 1 Jan., 1 Aug. 1756, 2 items (5 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Deeds, Bonds, Plats, Receipts, Accounts, 1760-1769, 11 items (17 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Deeds, 1770-1778, 5 items (12 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Plats, Receipt, Deed, Patent, Letter, 1782-1789, 6 items (11 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Deeds, Accounts, Release, Bonds, Receipts, Letter, Plat, Grant, 1791-1799, 18 items (26 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter, Certificate, Receipts, 1801-1806, 4 items (4 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Receipts, Deeds, Commission, Survey, 1810-1819, 18 items (24 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter, Deeds, Plat, Receipts, Survey, Pedigree, 1822-1829, 13 items (22 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Deeds, Receipts, Power of Attorney, Survey, 1830-1839, 10 items (22 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Account, Receipts, Deed, 1840-1843, 4 items (6 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Surveys, Plats, Notes, Receipts, n.d., 8 items (10 negative photostats) (Box 1, Folder 11)